<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>LinzJax:</title>
    <description>A collection of all of my thoughts, notes, and musings in one jumbled incoherent mess.
</description>
    <link>http://linzjax.github.io/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://linzjax.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Mon, 18 Jan 2016 11:45:18 -0500</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 18 Jan 2016 11:45:18 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.5.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Outreachy and the messy reality of UI</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I had set aside my sketchbook, put the finishing touches on my wireframes, settled on one of them, and sat down to build a stand alone version of Field Papers. All my brilliant ideas for an improved UI were dancing around in my mind, excited to be turned into a reality that users would be thanking me for for years to come. Then, like a kid who’s finally discovered that Santa’s not real, I realized that nothing was as simple and glittery as I had hoped.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay, so I’m being a bit over-dramatic. Still, there’s nothing quite like that sinking, humbling feeling of reality setting in. It turns out creating the perfect UI for Field Papers is a messy ordeal. It’s a nice reminder that I am, in fact, still learning. However, the perfectionist in me was none too pleased with this situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s take a journey together on my train of thought, to see what happened as the project went along:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Grid stays centered.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My biggest beef with the old Field Papers was that the grid didn’t move with you as you panned around, so let’s fix that! Everything is nice and centered, and when you go to add more rows and columns the map politely zooms out to let you cover the area you’re trying to access… oh wait, what if that’s not the are you wanted to cover? What if you zoomed in to the exact area you wanted to cover and now you’re frustrated that it’s zooming and jumping all over the place? Hm… ok…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Grid stays front and centered the entire time.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is perfect. It’s like looking through the lens of a camera. You find the area you want to cover, add rows and columns to fit your desires, and voila! All done. It’s only covering the area that you’re looking at, no obnoxious jumping around, the grid and the map are now two totally separate things. Simple, easy, no bells and whistles. But wait… the zoom on Leaflet is really aggressive, so it’s really hard to get just the area that I want to cover.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Grid stays front and centered the entire time with a resize scaling button in the corner.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alright, the grid stays in the view your looking at, and now you can adjust the size of the grid to exactly what you needed it to be. Just one whistle, that’s fine, nothing too complicated. Wait… What if because of how far you had to zoom out to keep it centered, you have no idea what you’re actually looking at? You now can’t tell what details are in each individual square!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;…. okaaay…..&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Grid stays front and centered the entire time with a resize scaling button in the corner and ability to lock it in place.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok, this time I’ve got it. The grid stays in place unless you lock it in place, which gives you the ability to pan and zoom without the grid moving at all. Wait, this is just the old UI with less mobility! Ugh, and now all of my calculations are wrong, and things aren’t able to update the way that they should, and what if…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What if situation [x, y, z, fish, etc]??&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are so many caveats. So many! This spiral went on for quite some time. Something I had pictured so perfectly in my mind was slowly falling apart in front of me. After a nice cup of warm tea and a chat with my mentor Ian, he helped me come to the realization that it doesn’t have to be perfect. In fact, it doesn’t even have to be great. It just has to be better than what’s already there. Besides, how are we going to know what works best without other people messing around with it and pointing out all of its flaws? We can worry about fine tuning and nitpicking in future iterations, but there’s no need to start pulling hair out just yet. It would be unreasonable to expect a perfect UI first go around, without any user input or research. This is a process with many steps involved, and I shouldn’t (read “can’t”) skip any of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After taking a few slow, deep breaths, I’ve started winding up my initial ui-experiments into something not perfect, but good enough. I’ll hopefully be passing them off for other people to debate about in the near future. In the mean time, Ian suggested that we work together to learn a little bit of Ruby on Rails, and I’m super excited! Full-stack here I come!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until next time!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 08 Jan 2016 07:12:09 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://linzjax.github.io/outreachy/2016/01/08/outreachy-and-the-messy-reality-of-ui.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://linzjax.github.io/outreachy/2016/01/08/outreachy-and-the-messy-reality-of-ui.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>outreachy</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>New Years Cliché</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;oh-new-years&quot;&gt;Oh New Years.&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A time for delusional fantasies and misplaced hopes. At least it provides motivation for me to finally get a gym membership. If I missed out on months of beautiful running weather because I “wasn’t feelin’ it”, there’s no way in hell I’m going to convince myself to go running when New York finally decides it’s time for winter. Maybe between a half-baked new year’s resolution and a $20 a month fee I’ll finally get my butt back in shape again (not that my butt doesn’t already have a lovely shape, but you know).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eye-rolling sighs aside, this really is something I need to do. My health isn’t what it used to be. My stomach can’t handle eating three slices of cheesecake a day, no matter how hard I might try. Feeling tired, exhausted, and a kinda sad all the time is not really how I want to spend my time. So, after a few difficult goodbyes to my junk food collection and an awkward re-acquaintance with my tennis shoes (“oh, it’s you again…”), I’ve decided to start this blog as a way to keep myself accountable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;my-goals&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;My Goals&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Honestly, no section should start with “My Goals”. “What I hope to accomplish if maybe, for once, I can hold myself accountable to something longer than it takes to say ‘gosh my bed is warm’” would be much closer to the truth. Anyway…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;30 Day Reset&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My biggest problem is that Hashimotos has been kicking my butt for over a year now. My lab results are normal, but my gut and my brain are telling me otherwise. I’m going to stick to a 30 day reset with the AIP Protocol in an attempt to straighten things out, see how I feel, and then slowly introduce things back in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Go to the gym (more than once)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Biggest perk of being in NYC: there are two gyms on the same block that I live. No excuses. If I’m spending $20 a month on a gym membership, I need to spend 20 hours a month (at least) in there. My knees aren’t what they used to be, and having a job that has me stuck at a desk for eight hours isn’t exactly helping me maintain my current physical status.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Learn to play the guitar/tennis/rock climb/etc…&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I miss music. I miss being active. I used to be really good at both of those things, and it’s darn well time I brought them back into my life. Going to the gym is all well and good, but it should be for the goal of helping me get better at an activity I love, or don’t know that I love yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Get a tech job&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve dug my grave, now it’s time to lie in it. I quit my job, jumped off the deep end, and now it’s time to convince not only myself but others that I have skills that are useful and employable. I’m going to finish reading Eloquent Javascript, I’m going to stop having panic attacks at every Leet Code challenge, and I’m going to finally understand algorithms. Gonna do it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Stop spending hours on social media&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why do I do this? Why do I care? It’s like my brain doesn’t know what to do if it’s not constantly entertained. I’m going to get a bedside clock so that I’m not tempted to stay in bed and stare at my phone. I’m going to start being more aware of my knee jerk reaction to open those apps. I’m going to find something more useful with my time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are so many other things that I could list here, but I feel like this is a good start for the next few months, which is how I’m going to do this. A year is a very long time, and can seem daunting. A few months though, that’s not bad. I can reward myself after a few months, re-evaluate my goals, and start again. We’ll see how it goes!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 03 Jan 2016 07:09:09 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://linzjax.github.io/my-experiences/2016/01/03/New-Years-Cliche.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://linzjax.github.io/my-experiences/2016/01/03/New-Years-Cliche.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>my-experiences</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Research, Rethink, and Redesign</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“Avoid pixel-pushing at all costs – your job is to solve problems. View your work through that lens at all times. […] Accurately defining the problem goes a long way towards solving it.” - &lt;a href=&quot;http://somerandomdude.com/2012/01/10/transition-from-development-to-design/&quot;&gt;J.P. Onori&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;getting-started&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Getting started&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s week three of my internship with Cadasta, and I have been working on a complete redesign of the UI for &lt;a href=&quot;http://fieldpapers.org/&quot;&gt;Field Papers&lt;/a&gt;. Field Papers is an open source mapping tool that allows users to select areas on an atlas grid to be printed out, taken into the field, and then loaded back onto Field Papers. The concept of Field Papers is simple in theory, and it wasn’t until I started actually trying to improve it that I realized how complicated it was, but I’ll talk more about that in the next blog post (teasers!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;As I started digging into Field Papers there were a few &lt;em&gt;seemingly&lt;/em&gt; simple issues that stood out to me:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1) The map was way too small to actually be able to successfully navigate the atlas grid positioning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2) The atlas grid movement was completely disconnected from the map movement, which was confusing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3) The process was broken down into three separate steps, and could be consolidated into a single page site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4) Adding rows and columns was complicated by the fact that the buttons ran away from you as you clicked on them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the suggestion of my mentor Ian, I focused on three ways to solve most of these problems: &lt;strong&gt;“demodalisation”&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;“big map”&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;“better UI interaction model”&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Demodalization involves combining all three map composition steps onto a single page, and doing away with the “wizard” mode. Big map, rather unsurprisingly, consists of turning the current tiny map view port into a full screen map view. This will give the user much more flexibility and room to maneuver. Creating a better UI interaction model has turned out to be much more complicated and less straight forward than anticipated. But, again, I will discuss this in more detail in my next post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Addressing these issues needed to start with creating a full screen map display that could incorporate all possible map interactions onto a single page. Rather than jumping straight into building, I started with research, sketches and wireframes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;research&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Research&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first task was to see &lt;a href=&quot;http://linzjax.github.io/fieldpapers/notes-page/&quot;&gt;what other people were doing&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div width=&quot;100%&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gallery-box&quot;&gt;
		&lt;div class=&quot;gallery-images&quot;&gt;
			&lt;div class=&quot;image&quot;&gt;
				&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/FogukeV.png&quot; /&gt;
			&lt;/div&gt;
			&lt;div class=&quot;image&quot;&gt;
				&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/d4BSjNQ.png&quot; /&gt;
			&lt;/div&gt;
			&lt;div class=&quot;image&quot;&gt;
				&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/fIX7Fz3.png&quot; /&gt;
			&lt;/div&gt;
			&lt;div class=&quot;image&quot;&gt;
				&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/NIIn93o.png&quot; /&gt;
			&lt;/div&gt;
			&lt;div class=&quot;image&quot;&gt;
				&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/p3ICXGH.png&quot; /&gt;
			&lt;/div&gt;
			&lt;div class=&quot;image&quot;&gt;
				&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/aWzWT2l.png&quot; /&gt;
			&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gallery-lightbox hidden&quot;&gt;
	&lt;div class=&quot;gallery-lightbox-image&quot;&gt;
		&lt;img src=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;[&lt;em&gt;Examples of other websites with large scale maps. Most of them include a large side menu.&lt;/em&gt;]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Turns out that there’s not a whole lot of variation in the world of full screen maps. Unfortunately, there can’t be. If the goals is to allow the user to interact with the map, layouts and menus should be as unobtrusive as possible. There’s no need to be clever and cute. Just get out of the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;After examining what the current trends are, I came to a few conclusions:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only use lightbox menus for specific purposes. &lt;br /&gt;
	There were a few sites that used them for every action. It turned out to be distracting and frustrating. Not only were they in the way of the map view, they didn’t allow me to quickly flip back and forth between actions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Icons without explanation can be more confusing that they’re worth. &lt;br /&gt;
	I’ve run across this in a few apps, where in attempt to be as clean and streamlined as possible they turn all of their buttons into icons. This is all well and good, but only if it’s &lt;em&gt;extremely clear&lt;/em&gt; exactly what each icon represents. (I’m looking at you viscocam….)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Placement of menus should be simple and consistent. &lt;br /&gt;
	Having menus along all four walls of the browser window feels cluttered, and doesn’t allow your eyes to rest. Try to keep it limited to two walls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having the option to toggle whether or not the menu is visible is nice. &lt;br /&gt;
	However, and this goes along with the icon point, it should be clear how to trigger this interaction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Separate actions into different menus only if it makes sense. &lt;br /&gt;
	You want to make sure the separations make sense and are organized in a manner that’s not confusing to the user.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re ever uncertain, include a help section. &lt;br /&gt;
	If you think any of the interaction or icons might be confusing, include a help section. Heck, even if you don’t think it’s confusing, &lt;em&gt;include a help section&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;rethink&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rethink&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After my initial research and with these notes in mind, I settled down to do a quick 20 minute sketch session. The purpose of this exercise was to get as many ideas as I could in the allotted time, and to not stop until the timer was done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;instagram-media&quot; data-instgrm-captioned=&quot;&quot; data-instgrm-version=&quot;6&quot; style=&quot; background:#FFF; border:0; border-radius:3px; box-shadow:0 0 1px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.5),0 1px 10px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.15); margin: 1px; max-width:658px; padding:0; width:60%; width:-webkit-calc(60% - 2px); width:calc(60% - 2px);&quot;&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;padding:8px;&quot;&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; background:#F8F8F8; line-height:0; margin-top:40px; padding:47.4074074074% 0; text-align:center; width:100%;&quot;&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; background:url(data:image/png;base64,iVBORw0KGgoAAAANSUhEUgAAACwAAAAsCAMAAAApWqozAAAAGFBMVEUiIiI9PT0eHh4gIB4hIBkcHBwcHBwcHBydr+JQAAAACHRSTlMABA4YHyQsM5jtaMwAAADfSURBVDjL7ZVBEgMhCAQBAf//42xcNbpAqakcM0ftUmFAAIBE81IqBJdS3lS6zs3bIpB9WED3YYXFPmHRfT8sgyrCP1x8uEUxLMzNWElFOYCV6mHWWwMzdPEKHlhLw7NWJqkHc4uIZphavDzA2JPzUDsBZziNae2S6owH8xPmX8G7zzgKEOPUoYHvGz1TBCxMkd3kwNVbU0gKHkx+iZILf77IofhrY1nYFnB/lQPb79drWOyJVa/DAvg9B/rLB4cC+Nqgdz/TvBbBnr6GBReqn/nRmDgaQEej7WhonozjF+Y2I/fZou/qAAAAAElFTkSuQmCC); display:block; height:44px; margin:0 auto -44px; position:relative; top:-22px; width:44px;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt; &lt;p style=&quot; margin:8px 0 0 0; padding:0 4px;&quot;&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/p/_FByZCy9GR/&quot; style=&quot; color:#000; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; font-style:normal; font-weight:normal; line-height:17px; text-decoration:none; word-wrap:break-word;&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Sketchy sketch is sketchy. #outreachy #noideawhatimdoing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p style=&quot; color:#c9c8cd; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px; margin-bottom:0; margin-top:8px; overflow:hidden; padding:8px 0 7px; text-align:center; text-overflow:ellipsis; white-space:nowrap;&quot;&gt;A photo posted by Linz Jax (@linzjaxx) on &lt;time style=&quot; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px;&quot; datetime=&quot;2015-12-09T16:56:40+00:00&quot;&gt;Dec 9, 2015 at 8:56am PST&lt;/time&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; defer=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//platform.instagram.com/en_US/embeds.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This exercise prevented me from spending much time focusing on any one idea, which prevented me from becoming attached and letting that influence all of my subsequent decisions. It also prevented me from worrying about &lt;em&gt;completing&lt;/em&gt; each design idea. That way, when I started building wireframes I could choose the best options out of a pile of ideas and &lt;em&gt;then&lt;/em&gt; allow myself to finish them. A lot of the sketches ended up looking the same, but they still fed ideas once I actually started building out the models. There aren’t many options when it comes to being unobtrusive, and that’s ok.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During this process, I also brainstormed different ways each interaction could be designed. When does a dropdown vs. buttons make sense? Are there ways that tasks can be separated into different actions (map adjustment actions vs. saving and note-taking actions).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://rippedshakespear.mybalsamiq.com/projects/testing/zoom%20one.jpeg?version=3&amp;amp;etag=Z.sD2JZ1pxArJw4Q9iBMzMSqTlptAQHg&quot; alt=&quot;interactions&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;redesign&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Redesign&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once I was done with that I moved onto wireframes. I used &lt;a href=&quot;https://balsamiq.com/&quot;&gt;Balsamiq&lt;/a&gt; to build my &lt;a href=&quot;https://rippedshakespear.mybalsamiq.com/projects/testing/prototype/large%20left%20menue?key=a58b5f9011225b47db50f4fcf34c7cffdd2941cc&quot;&gt;wireframes&lt;/a&gt;, and oh my gosh it was magical. Incredibly easy to use, and little to no learning curve. Since this was the first time I had really worked with a wireframing tool, I started with the initially suggested design (with a few tweaks of my own). After that, I tried to implement as many different designs as I could, and ended up with about eight. I tried to make several that were very different, as well as a few I knew just straight up wouldn’t work. I wanted to build these anyway just to see &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; it wouldn’t work and what it was about these designs that made me uncomfortable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;These are a few examples of uncomfortable designs:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;gallery-box&quot;&gt;
	&lt;div class=&quot;gallery-images&quot;&gt;
		&lt;div class=&quot;image&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;https://rippedshakespear.mybalsamiq.com/projects/testing/round%20the%20outside%20menus.jpeg?version=2&amp;amp;etag=BeCO0B5dMODWGAMxwP9YXg_Gv5hIe5fm&amp;amp;key=a58b5f9011225b47db50f4fcf34c7cffdd2941cc&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;div class=&quot;image&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;https://rippedshakespear.mybalsamiq.com/projects/testing/weird%20top%20menu.jpeg?version=4&amp;amp;etag=qp3WHKbUxv50L.Fy1vIjOgxBAyOiW.CN&amp;amp;key=a58b5f9011225b47db50f4fcf34c7cffdd2941cc&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;div class=&quot;image&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;https://rippedshakespear.mybalsamiq.com/projects/testing/Top%20banner%20and%20%5Blightbox%5D.jpeg?version=8&amp;amp;etag=.cmR5zy86tMTcZVMEWUMU9hHFpLSE.tF&amp;amp;key=a58b5f9011225b47db50f4fcf34c7cffdd2941cc&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Image one&lt;/strong&gt;: You can’t see anything because the text lacks a background. Also, by placing the menu all the way around the edges your eyes are never given the chance to rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Image two&lt;/strong&gt;: The design just feels old, and while the positioning of the options are similar to the original Field Papers, it doesn’t feel like an improvement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Image three&lt;/strong&gt;: While initially I liked this design, it still presents the problem of tasks being separated a bit too harshly. It also doesn’t allow the user to write notes until they’re &lt;em&gt;done&lt;/em&gt; with the map, which is not ideal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After pushing myself to come up with as many ideas as possible, I was then able to narrow down my selection to three, and have a much better idea of &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; I preferred these designs over others. These were my final three:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This first one combines all of the task into one side menu. Everything is in one place, easily found, and always present. 
&lt;img width=&quot;100%&quot; src=&quot;https://rippedshakespear.mybalsamiq.com/projects/testing/large%20left%20menue.jpeg?version=7&amp;amp;etag=NIJfjEYtJfOwh0jkwcmrRA_p04lKOc.A&amp;amp;key=a58b5f9011225b47db50f4fcf34c7cffdd2941cc&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This second one separates all of the actions into their own icon, allowing the user to think of them as different components to be tweaked on at a time. Stays as unobtrusive as possible.
&lt;img width=&quot;100%&quot; src=&quot;https://rippedshakespear.mybalsamiq.com/projects/testing/umap%20esqu%20%5Bpaper%5D.jpeg?version=3&amp;amp;etag=KSrrkEWdLWvb368g6.7NMTpzL7VUwKdn&amp;amp;key=a58b5f9011225b47db50f4fcf34c7cffdd2941cc&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This third one combines the first two ideas. It separates the actions into two categories, and provides a more solid menu to navigate. 
&lt;img width=&quot;100%&quot; src=&quot;https://rippedshakespear.mybalsamiq.com/projects/testing/Left%20button%20right%20menu%20%5Bgrid%5D.jpeg?version=4&amp;amp;etag=hwonxcPIL_sIkJgerw8MkR3msBQ3iWrk&amp;amp;key=a58b5f9011225b47db50f4fcf34c7cffdd2941cc&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After talking it over with the Cadasta team, we ended up deciding on the first one. It ensures that all of the options are present, and completely removes the issue of modalization that was so problematic with the initial Field Papers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-thoughts&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Final thoughts&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was glad that I had the time to spend on going through this process. It allowed me to really think through all of the decisions I was making, rather than just running with whatever idea popped into my head first. Also, designing out in the open was valuable because it prevented me from developing this idea that these designs were &lt;em&gt;mine&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;precious&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;private&lt;/em&gt;. It allowed me to get comfortable with other people’s thoughts and opinions, and my designs only improved as a result.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So on to the next step! I am currently working on building a stand alone version of the tool to see how it actually behaves. Up next: The messy reality of UI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until next time,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cheers!&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 24 Dec 2015 08:33:09 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://linzjax.github.io/outreachy/2015/12/24/research-rethink-redesign.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://linzjax.github.io/outreachy/2015/12/24/research-rethink-redesign.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>outreachy</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Hello Outreachy</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;It’s been two months since I applied, one month since I found out I got accepted, and four days since the beginning of the Outreachy internship, and yet somehow, &lt;em&gt;somehow&lt;/em&gt; I’m still in denial about the fact that it’s actually happening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;But it is.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;How cool is that?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I’ve set aside my denial and decided to tell the world about my Outreachy journey. (Also, it’s a requirement of the internship, but I would have done it anyway. No really. Don’t look at me like that.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I was finishing up my batch at the Recurse Center, reality was starting to set in. If I really want to turn this hobby into a career, I have to start convincing other people (and myself) that I know what I’m doing. Outreachy seemed like a great place to start.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those that don’t know, &lt;a href=&quot;https://gnome.org/outreachy/&quot;&gt;Outreachy&lt;/a&gt; is a project that works to help underrepresented members of the tech community get involved in open source. You get to spend three months working with one of their partner companies on a project they’ve outlined. Open source has been an integral part of my journey to become a developer (see my &lt;a href=&quot;http://linzjax.github.io/my/experiences/2015/10/29/why-open-source-is-important-for-new-coders.html&quot;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt; for more open source banner waving), and I was excited by the opportunity to continue working within the community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So here I am, and I am so excited to be working with Cadasta! I’m thrilled to have the opportunity to combine design and development as I work with their team to rethink and redesign Field Papers’ UI. Over the next few weeks I’ll be blogging about my progress and musings along the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First installment: Research, rethink and redesign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until next time!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 10 Dec 2015 07:09:09 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://linzjax.github.io/outreachy/2015/12/10/hello-outreachy.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://linzjax.github.io/outreachy/2015/12/10/hello-outreachy.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>outreachy</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Reflections on Recurse Center</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;And just like that it was over. If you had told me a year ago that I would quit my job, move to New York and attend a completely self-directed three month “writers retreat” for programmers, I would have laughed nervously and not made eye contact. Yet here I am, makin’ eye contact like a pro. It’s been an unbelievable three months. I’ve made an amazing group of friends, and learned so much it makes my head hurt to think about it. I went into Recurse thinking GUI was a way to describe brownies and came out of it being able to comfortably construct full-stack applications like a boss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reflecting back on my experience, I realized that there were a lot of things I wish I had known, or maybe had a heads up for what to expect. So, for future Recursers: here are my thoughts. Hopefully they’ll help someone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. It’s ok to spend time just learning.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I got to Recurse I was asked over and over again “So what are you working on?”. It wasn’t until the second half of my batch that I realized this is Recurse equivalent of “how are you doing?”. It wasn’t meant to be intimidating. It wasn’t meant to suggest that I had to have a project idea right then and there. It was genuinely because people were interested. That being said, it was still horribly intimidating. I barely knew enough JavaScript to put together a tictactoe game. How was I going to come up with a full scale project?!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m going to tell you a little secret: what you’re working on doesn’t have to be a project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spent the first few weeks going through Node.js, Mongodb and Express tutorials, making sure that I really understood how they worked, and only then did I start working on projects. Recurse isn’t a startup factory, you don’t need to constantly be churning out some shiny new thing. It’s good to set goals, and it’s goood to have things you want to accomplish, but a good project could be going through all of Eloquent JavaScript.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, make sure you don’t spend the entire time with your nose tucked into a tutorial. Find someone else who wants to learn the same thing. Find someone who already knows about this stuff and ask them questions if you’re confused. There are people at Recurse. Use them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. Don’t be afraid to ask questions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I first got to Recurse, I was terrified of asking questions. Being rather new to programming, I assumed my questions were stupid, I was wasting people’s time, and they were silently wondering what the hell I was doing at Recurse if I didn’t already know these things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After finally getting up the courage to start asking, I was amazing at how excited people were to help. Recurse is filled with people that are interested in learning, and excited about others learning as well, and they want to help! Rather than banging my head against my keyboard hoping Google would come up with some magic tutorial, I could ask someone to explain, and then continue to explain if I didn’t get it the first time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, I’ve learned to love the phrase “I don’t know what that means”. You always learn something new, and if that person isn’t quite sure either, you get to learn together! It’s the best.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. Work with other people&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pairing with people is scary. The first time I did I found myself replaying it in my head going “Oh god was I annoying? Did I slow them down? Was this actually something they wanted to work on?”. What I can tell you now is not to worry about it. Talk about what you’re interested in working on ahead of time and make sure that you both have the same goals. If you want to dive deep and really understand things, and they just want to finish the project, you’re not going to have a great time pairing. If you didn’t enjoy pairing with someone, don’t worry about it. If they don’t ask you to pair again, don’t worry about it. It’s all a learning experience, and there are no wrong decisions, except the decision not to work with anyone while you’re there. Mostly because you need to know how. If you want to program as a career, you need to know how to pair, and Recurse is a safe place to practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. Shits and giggles programming is just the best&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were several times that I was working on a “real” project, hating my life, and finally ditching it to build something fun and stupid. These fun and stupid projects ended up being some of my favorite. It’s okay to have fun. It’s okay to build something useless just because you feel like it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5. Learn to walk away&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re staring angrily at your computer screen, slamming your keys desperately trying to fix a bug that you know would be easily fixed if you could just figure out what the stupid thing is doing wrong. Walk. Away. Get up from your seat, pace the room, grab a cup of tea, ask people if they’re interested in a coffee run, anything. Just walk away. Your brain has this amazing ability to figure things out, but only if you give it a chance to recuperate. You’ll be amazed what comes to you after you’ve walked away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;6. Talk to people!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m the worst at networking. I think it’s silly and I find small talk painful at best. However, for the first few weeks of Recurse I made it a point to talk to as many different people as possible. It was scary, but everyone was incredibly open, and I learned a lot about my fellow Recursers. One of things that makes Recurse unique is that everyone is “the new person”, so they’re all looking for someone to talk to. It’s like a beautiful hand crafted artisanal friend group made specifically for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you feel like you haven’t really made connections with anyone immediately, give it time. Some of my best friends from Recurse I didn’t talk to until the second half.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;7. Do things that scare the hell out of you.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of the following points lead into this: Practice being brave.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recurse is one of the most supporting, loving, non-judgmental environments I’ve ever been in. No one’s doing a “thing”. No one’s looking at you funny. Everyone’s going to be excited when you join in and try new things. Before Recurse I had never sung a song at karaoke by myself. Ever. Not once. But the first karaoke night I decided I was going to do it because everyone else was having fun and no one cared that we weren’t going to be auditioning for American Idol any time soon, and everyone cheered so loud after every song that you felt like you were the biggest rock star in the world. My voice cracked, I was scared out of my mind, but I survived. Not only did I survive, I got thoroughly addicted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While this point acts as a plug for karaoke night (please keep this tradition going!), it’s mostly to highlight the importance of doing the things that scare you. Avoiding things because “you’re not good at them” is silly. It’s a fixed mindset that’s going to keep you from rocking out like Christina Aguilera wishes she could. Be brave! Do things!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recurse is amazing. You’re amazing. You’d make a great pair. If you’re thinking about going, you totally should. If you’re still unsure, or have more questions, please don’t hesitate to ask me anything. I have so much advice and many stories to share. My next blog will be on the scary bits of Recurse (don’t worry, they’re not that scary). Until then,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cheers!&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 11 Nov 2015 13:30:09 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://linzjax.github.io/my/experiences/2015/11/11/reflections-on-recurse-center.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://linzjax.github.io/my/experiences/2015/11/11/reflections-on-recurse-center.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>my</category>
        
        <category>experiences</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Why participating in open source is important for new coders</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;As &lt;a href=&quot;https://hacktoberfest.digitalocean.com/&quot;&gt;#Hacktober&lt;/a&gt; is coming to a close, I’ve been reflecting on my experience with open source. When I initially started learning to code, it was pretty daunting with the amount of information out there. There’s a lot of people with a lot of advice (I know because I asked just about everyone I could). One of the biggest hurdles that I ran into was knowing when I was getting past the “&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.vikingcodeschool.com/posts/why-learning-to-code-is-so-damn-hard&quot;&gt;hand holding honeymoon&lt;/a&gt;” phase into working on “real” projects. The “handholding honeymoon phase” occurs when you’re just starting out and beginner tutorials are walking you through carefully constructed problems with carefully constructed solutions and oh my gosh you just built something congratulations! You’ve learned the basics of coding!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;But what now?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What should the next steps be? There are so many tutorials out there, and so many different languages and frameworks, and new ones coming out every day. How do you begin to learn what you don’t know, especially when you don’t even know what you don’t know?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The advice that I got over and over again was just to work on a project. Doesn’t matter what, just build something. But that means coming up with an idea, and then a plan for how to build it, and then figuring out how all of the pieces fit together. That’s not daunting or overwhelming at all, especially when you’re used to beginner tutorials that have the framework and design already set up, and now you have to figure out everything that goes into making something a “real” app and you have no idea how to make user accounts or set up databases and servers and what the heck is a framework?! It was almost enough to convince me to just stick to bartending.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thankfully I’ve made it past this consistently overwhelmed phase, and open source projects were a huge player in getting me through this slump.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gaining confidence in your own ability&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was lucky enough to have a group of coding friends who were extremely supportive and wanted to teach me everything they knew, and I remember one of them sitting me down to walk through contributing to an open source project that needed help. She pointed out a bug, then walked me through where things lived in the code (and how to read where things lived), and then patiently waited as I remembered my basic python and what could be done to fix the problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All it was was string manipulation. I knew how to do that. That’s not a real project. If I know how to do that that’s not &lt;strong&gt;real&lt;/strong&gt; coding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it was. That was all it took, and just like that I had made my first commit and my first pull request. I spent the rest of the day riding between a high of “I did it!” and “wait… that’s it?”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And yes, that was it. Just like that I was hooked. The developers passed along any simple bugs they ran into for me to work through. Even though they might have been able to find it and fix it faster, they knew that allowing me time to sort through all of this new code, translate it, and practice fixing things was invaluable, so they happily let me do it. I gained so much confidence and experience from being able to make positive changes to real code every day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The open source community wants to help themselves by helping you.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This really taught me to appreciate the open source community. Getting into coding is scary, and encouragement is an absolute necessity. Because the open source community benefits so much from helping each other and from helping new people getting involved, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.erikaheidi.com/blog/a-beginners-guide-to-open-source-making-your-first-contribution?utm_medium=community&amp;amp;utm_source=hacktoberfest&amp;amp;utm_campaign=digest1&quot;&gt;they are endlessly nurturing&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It still amazes me how much time people are willing to set aside to review, edit, re-review and re-edit code to make sure that you’re submitting your absolute best work. You get to work on projects, get code review, and benefit the community at large all in one go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Getting code reviewed can initially be very intimidating. It might seem like they’re being super nitpicky or their standards are too high or you’re not good enough, but really they’re helping you write better code for everyone’s sake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another great thing about this community is that no contribution is too small. You’re not expected (nor would they necessarily want you to) completely overhaul their code with some new feature. Even editing the READMe’s to be more accessible and understandable is appreciated. If there’s a tiny little glitch that you think is insignificant, fix it anyway! Maybe they just haven’t gotten around to it and you’re saving them the trouble.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I was lucky enough to have friends to walk me through the first step, I’ve run across plenty of projects that have set aside issues with directions to what file the problem lives in so you only have to focus on one file. Some projects have even put together a list of “low hanging fruit” problems that need to be fixed. They want your help, and are trying to make it as easily as possible to contribute, so help!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, this isn’t to say that every open source project you come across is going to be scrambling over themselves to work with you and your code. I’ve been very fortunate to find projects that are welcoming and patient, and plenty of people have put together &lt;a href=&quot;https://hacktoberfest.digitalocean.com/?utm_medium=community&amp;amp;utm_source=hacktoberfest&amp;amp;utm_campaign=confirmationemail#projects&quot;&gt;great lists of projects&lt;/a&gt; to get started on. But don’t get discouraged if one that you find isn’t greeting you with open arms. Chalk it up as a learning experience and find a new one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It will help you learn to read new accents&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A skill that I have found invaluable is what I call understanding accents. I view learning to code in the same light as learning a foreign language. In my high school french class we had a set curriculum with the same soothing voice speaking french in a very clear, slow and precise accent, which was great. I understood french, and I could repeat it. Yay! Then we’d watch a video of real people actually speaking french and suddenly it all went out the window. It was always such a frustrating feeling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I started learning javascript, the same thing happened. You have carefully constructed code you work with, you learn to parrot that code, and you learn specific techniques for dealing with certain challenges and you start to feel pretty good about yourself. Then suddenly you’re out in the “real world” without these carefully constructed problems and no handlebars (well maybe &lt;a href=&quot;http://handlebarsjs.com/&quot;&gt;Handlebars&lt;/a&gt;… Anyway…).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Staring at giant repositories of code was terrifying, but I started to force myself to look through the files until I found one in a language that I recognized. Then I would go through the file, looking up terms I didn’t recognize, slowly piecing the bits of the file together until it started to make sense. Sure, there were still chunks I didn’t quite understand, but it exposed me to a whole new variety of coding techniques, syntax, and problem solving. I was starting to understand different accents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Huge chunks of code can be intimidating when you’re just starting out, and the only way it’s going to get easier is if you practice navigating them. It taught me to comfortably block out all of the things that I don’t need and focus only on the code necessary to address the problem at hand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that #Hacktoberfest is coming to an end, but that doesn’t mean that you can’t still contribute to open source projects. It’s a never ending series of challenges to help you practice and get better, with people there to help you along the way, &lt;a href=&quot;https://guides.github.com/activities/contributing-to-open-source/?utm_medium=community&amp;amp;utm_source=hacktoberfest&amp;amp;utm_campaign=digest1&quot;&gt;so get started&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 29 Oct 2015 11:52:09 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://linzjax.github.io/my/experiences/2015/10/29/why-open-source-is-important-for-new-coders.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://linzjax.github.io/my/experiences/2015/10/29/why-open-source-is-important-for-new-coders.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>my</category>
        
        <category>experiences</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Getting virtualenvwrapper to stick around</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Virtual environments are awesome.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They allow you to install all of your required packages for one project without overriding your globally installed packages. If you want package version 3.0.3 for one project, and package version 2.7.4 for another, virtual environments are your friend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://virtualenv.readthedocs.org/en/latest/&quot;&gt;virtualenv&lt;/a&gt; does this for your python environments. It creates an environment with its own installation directories, separate from that of your usr/local/bin, so anything that you &lt;code&gt;pip install&lt;/code&gt; inside of a virtualenv, will only affect that project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To install virtualenv, open up your terminal and type in:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt; $ pip install virtualenv &lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To create a virutalenv instance, switch into your project directory:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt; $ cd my_project_folder &lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and make a new virtual environment:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt; $ virtualenv what_you_want_to_call_it &lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, in order to start your virtualenv, you’ll need to start it up using &lt;code&gt;source&lt;/code&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;http://bash.cyberciti.biz/guide/Source_command&quot;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt; activates a series of commands that only apply to that one terminal shell instance, and will end as soon as you close that shell. Which means that if you want to work in a virtualenv, you’ll need to run:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt; $ source what_you_want_to_call_it/bin/activate &lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;every&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;single&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;time.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, I found this tedious. &lt;a href=&quot;http://virtualenvwrapper.readthedocs.org/en/latest/&quot;&gt;virtualenvwrapper&lt;/a&gt; enables more human-readable commands… Sort of.
After you’ve installed virtualenv, you can:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ pip install virtualenvwrapper  
$ export WORKON_HOME=~/Envs  
$ source /usr/local/bin/virtualenvwrapper.sh  
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok, cool, now all you need to do is create a virtual environment:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt; $ mkvirtualenv your_virtual_env &lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and then open it up to work on:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt; $ workon your_virtual_env &lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To end your virtual environment session, all you have to do is deactivate:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ deactivate&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find this much more memorable, which is nice. But remember what I just said about &lt;code&gt;source&lt;/code&gt; ? How it only exists in that one shell instance? Yeah. That.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means when you open a new terminal window, you have to run this command:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ export WORKON_HOME=~/Envs  
$ source /usr/local/bin/virtualenvwrapper.sh
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;every&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;single&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;time.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Otherwise virtualenvwrapper disappears and none of the commands will work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So while, sure it’s more readable once you get things set up, you still have to constantly set things up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;But there’s a solution.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NOTE:&lt;/strong&gt; If you already use virtualenvwrapper, this will change where virtualenvwrapper looks for your virtual environments, so they won’t be accessible anymore, and you’ll need to recreate them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Open up your .bashrc file (or create one if you don’t have it.) &lt;a href=&quot;http://hacktux.com/bash/bashrc/bash_profile&quot;&gt;.bashrc&lt;/a&gt; contains a list of commands that are executed every time you open up a new terminal window.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;.bashrc will be located in your root ~/ directory.
In your terminal, type:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt; $ ls -a &lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;to see hidden files (ones that start with a .dot). Hopefully you’ll see it there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If not, type:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt; $ touch .bashrc &lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, regardless of it if already existed or you just created it, type:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt; $ open .bashrc -a &quot;Text Editor of Your Choice&quot; &lt;/code&gt; (capital letters in the application name matter. So I would type “Sublime Text 2”.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now add the three following lines of code:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;export WORKON_HOME=$HOME/.virtualenvs  
export PROJECT_HOME=$HOME/Devel

source /usr/local/bin/virtualenvwrapper.sh
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Save your .bashrc file, and restart your terminal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Now!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every time you open a new terminal shell, .bashrc will run those three lines of code for you, and the only thing you’ll have remember is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt; $ workon your_virtual_env &lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and you’re ready to go!&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 05 Oct 2015 11:52:09 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://linzjax.github.io/how-to/2015/10/05/making-virutalenvwrapper-stick-around.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://linzjax.github.io/how-to/2015/10/05/making-virutalenvwrapper-stick-around.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>how-to</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Getting Set Up</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;So if you’re wondering why this page is a mess, it’s because I spent most of today trying to manipulate an existing Jekyll theme (to little success as you can see). So I’ve decided to blow things up and start over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ll see what happens. In the meantime, pardon my mess.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2015 11:52:09 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://linzjax.github.io/jekyll/update/2015/09/01/Getting-set-up.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://linzjax.github.io/jekyll/update/2015/09/01/Getting-set-up.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>jekyll</category>
        
        <category>update</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
