<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>LinzJax:</title>
    <description>A collection of all of my thoughts, notes, and musings in one jumbled incoherent mess.
</description>
    <link>http://linzjax.github.io/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://linzjax.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Mon, 07 Mar 2016 17:13:17 -0500</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 07 Mar 2016 17:13:17 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.0.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Reflections on Outreachy</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I’ve written about Outreachy a number of times, but since today was my last day, I feel it’s appropriate to write one final summary post. Who doesn’t want a chance to tidy up all of their thoughts and put a nice bow on it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://gnome.org/outreachy/&quot;&gt;Outreachy&lt;/a&gt; is a program dedicated to getting underrepresented members of the tech community involved in open source software through paid internships with partner companies. Much to my excitement (and surprise) I was accepted as Cadasta’s Outreachy intern for the winter session. I had been teaching myself to code for less than a year but had absolutely fallen in love with it, so I quit my job to spent three months at the &lt;a href=&quot;recurse.com&quot;&gt;Recurse Center&lt;/a&gt; in order to fully immerse myself. Armed with enough knowledge to get by but not enough real experience to be dangerous, Outreachy was an exciting next step towards becoming a full-time developer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t know that I would have had the confidence to pursue coding as a career without the opportunity that Outreachy provided. Part of me was terrified at the thought of doing another internship. Right out of college, I got two internships back to back that both showed me (rather quickly) that the field I thought I wanted to get into was not for me, but they also didn’t feel like a solid step forward. I wasn’t fetching coffee, but the work I was given was minimal and intern (i.e. error) proof. Going into Outreachy I expected something similar. I expected to be handed an endless list of bugs to fix, and to be told exactly what to do, when to do it, and how. It made sense. I didn’t have a lot of experience. Why would I expect anything different?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Day one I found out how misguided my expectations were. Everyone at Cadasta was unbelievably welcoming, and I was given responsibility for the entire Field Papers user interface redesign, with the expectation that it would be treated the same as any other project. I was provided with guidance by people who advised me on where to start, who pointed me in the right direction when I got stuck, and helped me make the final decisions along the way. I had walked in expecting to be handed a blueprint, but was instead asked to write the blueprint, build the scaffolding, and make the final touches. Admittedly, it was a little nerve-racking, and I kept expecting someone to stop me once they discovered I was sort of winging it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But that was the point: this was an opportunity to learn how these projects work in a supportive and educational environment. I learned how to work with multiple companies on a single project, and that the end results of working with a team are vastly better than when you work alone without feedback. I learned to reach out frequently along the way to make sure I wasn’t getting too attached to any one idea in particular or getting off track. I learned how to work collaboratively and substantially on open source projects that had a real impact beyond bug fixes. Most importantly, I gained confidence in my own ability in a way that feels tangible because I can point to a project that I completed, that got the approval of multiple people along the way. The opportunity that Outreachy and Cadasta provided for me is invaluable, and I can’t thank or recommend them enough.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 07 Mar 2016 07:12:09 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://linzjax.github.io/outreachy/2016/03/07/reflections-on-outreachy.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://linzjax.github.io/outreachy/2016/03/07/reflections-on-outreachy.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>outreachy</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Rails, Turbolinks, and Event Listeners</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I finally learned to spell a-c-c-o-r-d-i-o-n. A few weeks ago, I was happily puttering along making my accordion menu for the new Field Papers UI (cue “oohs and aaahs”), when Ian pointed out that it sporadically wasn’t working. The menu items wouldn’t allow you to click on them, but refreshing the page seemed to fix it. After determining that this was indeed a bit odd, I set about to find a solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a bit more investigating, I determined that it only occurred when you started from a different page and then clicked on a link to the compose page. For example, I enter through the home url, click “Make an atlas”, and click forlornly on non-responsive accordion menus. Refresh the page, and triumphantly click on beautifully responsive accordion menus. This was a less than ideal situation, so after gathering evidence I discovered the culprit: &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/turbolinks/turbolinks&quot;&gt;Turbolinks&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Turbolinks is a Rails plugin that allows your rails app to behave like a single page application, and only loads the JavaScript and CSS once, instead of between each page change. In most circumstances, this would be fantastic. Faster load times, happier visitors, everyone wins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;BUT&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem that I was running into is that since Turbolinks runs all of the JavaScript files once, and only once, my poor event listeners were trying to find objects that didn’t exist and giving up hope after the first page load. This explains why it worked when you refreshed the page, but didn’t work when you started somewhere else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;$(document).on(&quot;ready&quot;, function(){
   //sad code that never happens :(
});
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thankfully, once the culprit was identified, the fix was rather simple. Turbolinks has its own events, so instead of &lt;em&gt;ready&lt;/em&gt; we listen for &lt;em&gt;page:change&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;$(document).on(&quot;page:change&quot;, function(){
   //happy code that&#39;s executed every time you go to a new page :D
});
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another option is to disable Turbolinks in all of the connecting &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;a&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; tags.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;a data-no-turbolink=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;&amp;lt;%= compose_path %&amp;gt;&quot;&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And voila! Your JavaScript and CSS are reloaded only on the important pages.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 24 Feb 2016 07:12:09 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://linzjax.github.io/outreachy/2016/02/24/rails-turbolinks-and-event-listeners.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://linzjax.github.io/outreachy/2016/02/24/rails-turbolinks-and-event-listeners.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>outreachy</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Handling remote work - pair programming with Cloud9</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;As my Outreachy internship moves along, and I’m learning just how much I love remote work. I love being able to set my own schedule, take a nap when I need to, cook during my lunch break, and workout when then gym’s not crowded. Also, my couch is really freakin comfortable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was initially worried about remote work because I love pairing with people. I can happily work by myself and look up answers when I get stuck (my google fu is on point), but the way that I really cement knowledge is by pairing with someone who knows more than I do. It’s a way for me to double check my assumptions, and clear up any confusions that I might have been glossing over. There’s also a really good chance I’ll learn something random, like new bash commands. I had gotten really used to doing this at Recurse Center because they encourage you to do it as much as possible, and I was worried about losing that opportunity when I started working remotely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;enter-cloud9&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Enter Cloud9&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://c9.io&quot;&gt;Cloud9&lt;/a&gt; was built primarily as an all inclusive development environment in the cloud. While this is great and all, it’s not really why I’m excited about it. I’m excited about it because it allows multiple people to work on the same project at once. It’s different from screen-sharing programs like &lt;a href=&quot;https://screenhero.com/&quot;&gt;Screenhero&lt;/a&gt; which constrain you to literally sharing the same screen. Cloud9 allows you to work on the same files, but yours screens don’t have to mirror each other. If we’re both looking at the same file, I can see the other person’s cursor and what they’re typing, but I’m not constrained to looking only at the file that they’re looking at. Pair programming I’ve done in the past is has consisted of one person talking and one person driving. This is definitely a different experience. I end up just saying my thought process out loud as I type, and then when I get stuck or want to see how they would do it, I ask. If we run into a bug, we can look in two separate areas and cover ground faster. While it does occasionally lead to both of us working on two separate things rather than both being engaged in one task, it feels more efficient and still provides the safety net of being able to ask questions and watch as they come up with solutions. The one glitch is that we both share the same terminal window, and whoever’s window happens to be smaller constrains the other person’s terminal. So my tiny laptop is seriously limiting to someone who has giant two monitors set up. They don’t handle private .files, so you have to edit these in the terminal using vim, and the server is pretty slow getting set up, but overall it is a pretty nice system. My favorite part: they handle merge conflicts like a dream.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t know that it would ever replace the work that I do on my local machine, but it certainly makes collaborative programming easy, and provides an environment that both a sublime and an emacs users can agree on. I give it two (or four if you’re pairing) thumbs up.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 12 Feb 2016 10:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://linzjax.github.io/outreachy/2016/02/12/handling-remote-work-pair-programming-with-cloud9.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://linzjax.github.io/outreachy/2016/02/12/handling-remote-work-pair-programming-with-cloud9.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>outreachy</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>First Major PR for Outreachy</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;its-done&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It’s done!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;blog-image&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://camo.githubusercontent.com/106be48a5af95926193a9f17d5af81889a1d0ea6/687474703a2f2f692e696d6775722e636f6d2f6771305646444e2e706e67&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, sort of. This week I submitted my first major pull request for all of the work I’ve been doing on Field Paper’s UI. After two months of &lt;a href=&quot;http://linzjax.github.io/outreachy/2015/12/24/research-rethink-redesign.html&quot;&gt;drawing up mocks&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://linzjax.github.io/outreachy/2016/01/08/outreachy-and-the-messy-reality-of-ui.html&quot;&gt;working through experiments&lt;/a&gt;, and putting together a working product, Ian and I finished putting all the pieces into something that’s actually functional. Is it any good? We’ll see, but at least it works!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During this last chunk of the process I’ve been learning enough Rails to get by. I’ve worked with Node and Flask in the past, so I have a solid understanding of the basic model view controller structure. I understand what routing is, and how to use template languages such as Jade and Handlebars. When I initially started going through the Rails tutorial, it seemed like familiar territory. But imagine setting out on a cross-country hike, and expecting to come across some challenges: a forest to stumble through, a mountain to scale. However, when you get there, someone’s already cut a clear path through the forest and put up a nice fence with a few benches along the way in case you get tired. They’ve also installed an elevator at the bottom of the mountain, so all that climbing gear you’ve been caring around now seems silly and useless. That’s how I felt learning Rails. I’ve implemented user accounts in the past using Passport, and all of the other libraries that are required to create secure user accounts, and along comes Rails with it’s magical User model generator and &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;has_secure_password&lt;/code&gt;. It’s very disorienting and makes you almost feel like you’re no longer involved in the process. It’s not that the elevator to the top of the mountain isn’t nice, you’re just vaguely suspicious because you can’t tell how it works and can’t see who’s operating it…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;blog-image-small&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://cdn02.wallpapersonweb.com/media/w1920x1080/cartoons2/27941-suspicious-fry-futurama-cartoon-desktop-wallpaper-1920x1080.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end I slogged (or strolled) through, and learned just enough Rails to be able to reconfigure my static Field Papers experiment into the original Field Papers ecosystem. Once it was up and running, it was time to re-write basically all of the CSS I had previously written. If I was going to fully integrate my changes into the original project, I needed to work with the asset pipeline, rather than try and shoehorn my !important changes in. After fiddling with a full-length menu, at the recommendation of both Chandra and Ian, I switched to an accordion menu. One of my favorite things to do in my spare time is learn how to build fancy things in CSS from other people on &lt;a href=&quot;http://codepen.io/&quot;&gt;CodePen&lt;/a&gt;. I ended up not only learning how to build an accordion menu, but also re-learned how to create triangles and arrows in pure css. (Sometimes, I think CSS is really cool. But don’t tell anyone.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p data-height=&quot;429&quot; data-theme-id=&quot;0&quot; data-slug-hash=&quot;jWZrwq&quot; data-default-tab=&quot;result&quot; data-user=&quot;linzjax&quot; class=&quot;codepen&quot;&gt;See the Pen &lt;a href=&quot;http://codepen.io/linzjax/pen/jWZrwq/&quot;&gt;Accordion Menu&lt;/a&gt; by Lindsey Jacks (&lt;a href=&quot;http://codepen.io/linzjax&quot;&gt;@linzjax&lt;/a&gt;) on &lt;a href=&quot;http://codepen.io&quot;&gt;CodePen&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//assets.codepen.io/assets/embed/ei.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s still plenty of room for improvement, which is why we’re currently conducting a survey to get feedback from the community. We’re hosting a &lt;a href=&quot;http://fieldpapers-demo.cadasta.org/&quot;&gt;demo platform&lt;/a&gt; where you can checkout the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/Cadasta/fieldpapers/wiki/Field-Papers-Menu-Mock-ups&quot;&gt;options for the side menu&lt;/a&gt;, as well as try out the UI experiments I rambled about in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://linzjax.github.io/outreachy/2016/01/08/outreachy-and-the-messy-reality-of-ui.html&quot;&gt;last blog post&lt;/a&gt;. Though the process is nowhere near complete, I’m really excited about the progress that I’ve made so far. This project has ended up being a really exciting challenge and a great way to solidify my skills and confidence. It feels really good to be able to point to something and say “I built that, and it’s actually helpful to other people”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until next time!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 05 Feb 2016 07:12:09 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://linzjax.github.io/outreachy/2016/02/05/first-major-pr-with-outreachy.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://linzjax.github.io/outreachy/2016/02/05/first-major-pr-with-outreachy.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>outreachy</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Admitting you don&#39;t know</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Have I bragged about Recurse, or Outreachy lately? Oh, I have? Well, I’m going to do it again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;reason-142-or-whatever--why-im-thankful-for-recurseoutreachy&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reason #142 (or whatever)  why I’m thankful for Recurse/Outreachy:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recurse provided me with the courage and enthusiasm to admit when I don’t know something, the excitement of being presented with completely new information, and the hubris to know that I could tackle any challenge put in front of me if given enough time and support. Saying “&lt;strong&gt;I don’t know what that is&lt;/strong&gt;” has become one of my favorite phrases. It’s not admitting defeat, it’s not revealing the fact that I secretly know nothing (buzz off imposter syndrome) - it’s an opportunity. They get to feel good about explaining something, and I get to learn something new. It’s a win-win situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I initially got into programming, I started in python, but it never really clicked for me. I spent the entire time wondering how the user was going to interact with it. What were they going to see? So, I switched to JavaScript since front-end had a greater appeal to me. However, now that I’m comfortable with JavaScript, I find myself worry about the exact opposite: Now I’ve got something pretty the user can interact with, but it doesn’t actually do anything. So when my mentor Ian took away my JavaScript crutches and asked if I wanted to learn Ruby on Rails I responded with a hearty “Hell yeah!” (ok I said something a little more of a professional like “Sure, I would love to”, but that doesn’t make for good blog rhetoric). I knew, due to the learning environment Outreachy and Cadasta had set up, this would be the perfect time to try something completely new. So being able to work with someone on back-end, someone who I’m actively encouraged to ask my stupid/basic/fundamental questions, is perfect. It’s been great having Ian and everyone else at Cadasta be so responsive to my “&lt;strong&gt;I don’t know&lt;/strong&gt;” questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;##&lt;strong&gt;Why the thought of leaving this comfortable bubble worries me:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m learning so much, and I’m having so much fun in this internship, but I’m aware that all good things must end. With March around the corner I’ve (unfortunately) started thinking about my next steps. While I’m excited about the prospect of finding my first “big kid” tech job, I’m concerned I’ll never find an environment like this again. I had forgotten that RC and Outreachy/Cadasta are the exception, not the rule when it comes to culture. I went to a JS meet up the other day, and I was surprised at the people I talked to that felt the need to puff their chest out when talking about their experience. It felt like they were walking around with a giant “try me” button.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The majority of the people were lovely, very excited about the work that they were doing, and just happy to be surrounded by other like-minded programmers. The moderators were amazing, and overall I had a ton of fun. However, those few people were an interesting reminder that a safe learning environment is not a guarantee. How do you foster a learning environment if people are secretly terrified of being discovered as frauds?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think Recurse Center’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.recurse.com/manual#sub-sec-social-rules&quot;&gt;social rules&lt;/a&gt; go a long way to solving this problem - no feigning surprise in particular. It makes it okay to admit ‘&lt;strong&gt;I don’t know&lt;/strong&gt;’ something, and creates a culture of excitement around introducing someone to something new. Rather than “HOW HAVE YOU NOT HEARD OF X, Y, AND Z?! HAVE YOU BEEN LIVING UNDER A ROCK?!” You get “OMG X, Y, AND Z IS AMAZING! COME! LET ME TAKE YOU ON A JOURNEY! YOU’RE GONNA LOVE IT!” It shifts the focus to building others up instead of putting them down. Who knows, maybe there was someone else who didn’t know about x, y, and z either. Now they get to learn something new rather than thanking their lucky stars they weren’t stupid enough to ask the question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel like it would be tough to judge this attitude in an interview process where admitting you don’t know something feels like writing a giant ¯_(ツ)_/¯ as an answer to a test question. Questions about mentorship and continued education only go so far as boiler plate answers, and besides, who says “nah, we hate that stuff” to a question like that. How do you really find out about the culture before signing on the dotted line?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-solution&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The solution?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I actually have no answers to this so…. ‘&lt;strong&gt;I don’t know!&lt;/strong&gt;’ (see what I did there?). So if anyone has any suggestions I’d love to hear them!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 25 Jan 2016 07:12:09 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://linzjax.github.io/outreachy/2016/01/25/Admitting-you-dont-know.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://linzjax.github.io/outreachy/2016/01/25/Admitting-you-dont-know.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>outreachy</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Outreachy and the messy reality of UI</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I had set aside my sketchbook, put the finishing touches on my wireframes, settled on one of them, and sat down to build a stand alone version of Field Papers. All my brilliant ideas for an improved UI were dancing around in my mind, excited to be turned into a reality that users would be thanking me for for years to come. Then, like a kid who’s finally discovered that Santa’s not real, I realized that nothing was as simple and glittery as I had hoped.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay, so I’m being a bit over-dramatic. Still, there’s nothing quite like that sinking, humbling feeling of reality setting in. It turns out creating the perfect UI for Field Papers is a messy ordeal. It’s a nice reminder that I am, in fact, still learning. However, the perfectionist in me was none too pleased with this situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s take a journey together on my train of thought, to see what happened as the project went along:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Grid stays centered.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My biggest beef with the old Field Papers was that the grid didn’t move with you as you panned around, so let’s fix that! Everything is nice and centered, and when you go to add more rows and columns the map politely zooms out to let you cover the area you’re trying to access… oh wait, what if that’s not the are you wanted to cover? What if you zoomed in to the exact area you wanted to cover and now you’re frustrated that it’s zooming and jumping all over the place? Hm… ok…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Grid stays front and centered the entire time.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is perfect. It’s like looking through the lens of a camera. You find the area you want to cover, add rows and columns to fit your desires, and voila! All done. It’s only covering the area that you’re looking at, no obnoxious jumping around, the grid and the map are now two totally separate things. Simple, easy, no bells and whistles. But wait… the zoom on Leaflet is really aggressive, so it’s really hard to get just the area that I want to cover.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Grid stays front and centered the entire time with a resize scaling button in the corner.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alright, the grid stays in the view your looking at, and now you can adjust the size of the grid to exactly what you needed it to be. Just one whistle, that’s fine, nothing too complicated. Wait… What if because of how far you had to zoom out to keep it centered, you have no idea what you’re actually looking at? You now can’t tell what details are in each individual square!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;…. okaaay…..&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Grid stays front and centered the entire time with a resize scaling button in the corner and ability to lock it in place.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok, this time I’ve got it. The grid stays in place unless you lock it in place, which gives you the ability to pan and zoom without the grid moving at all. Wait, this is just the old UI with less mobility! Ugh, and now all of my calculations are wrong, and things aren’t able to update the way that they should, and what if…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What if situation [x, y, z, fish, etc]??&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are so many caveats. So many! This spiral went on for quite some time. Something I had pictured so perfectly in my mind was slowly falling apart in front of me. After a nice cup of warm tea and a chat with my mentor Ian, he helped me come to the realization that it doesn’t have to be perfect. In fact, it doesn’t even have to be great. It just has to be better than what’s already there. Besides, how are we going to know what works best without other people messing around with it and pointing out all of its flaws? We can worry about fine tuning and nitpicking in future iterations, but there’s no need to start pulling hair out just yet. It would be unreasonable to expect a perfect UI first go around, without any user input or research. This is a process with many steps involved, and I shouldn’t (read “can’t”) skip any of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After taking a few slow, deep breaths, I’ve started winding up my initial ui-experiments into something not perfect, but good enough. I’ll hopefully be passing them off for other people to debate about in the near future. In the mean time, Ian suggested that we work together to learn a little bit of Ruby on Rails, and I’m super excited! Full-stack here I come!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until next time!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 08 Jan 2016 07:12:09 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://linzjax.github.io/outreachy/2016/01/08/outreachy-and-the-messy-reality-of-ui.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://linzjax.github.io/outreachy/2016/01/08/outreachy-and-the-messy-reality-of-ui.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>outreachy</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>New Years Cliché</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;oh-new-years&quot;&gt;Oh New Years.&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A time for delusional fantasies and misplaced hopes. At least it provides motivation for me to finally get a gym membership. If I missed out on months of beautiful running weather because I “wasn’t feelin’ it”, there’s no way in hell I’m going to convince myself to go running when New York finally decides it’s time for winter. Maybe between a half-baked new year’s resolution and a $20 a month fee I’ll finally get my butt back in shape again (not that my butt doesn’t already have a lovely shape, but you know).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eye-rolling sighs aside, this really is something I need to do. My health isn’t what it used to be. My stomach can’t handle eating three slices of cheesecake a day, no matter how hard I might try. Feeling tired, exhausted, and a kinda sad all the time is not really how I want to spend my time. So, after a few difficult goodbyes to my junk food collection and an awkward re-acquaintance with my tennis shoes (“oh, it’s you again…”), I’ve decided to start this blog as a way to keep myself accountable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;my-goals&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;My Goals&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Honestly, no section should start with “My Goals”. “What I hope to accomplish if maybe, for once, I can hold myself accountable to something longer than it takes to say ‘gosh my bed is warm’” would be much closer to the truth. Anyway…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;30 Day Reset&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My biggest problem is that Hashimotos has been kicking my butt for over a year now. My lab results are normal, but my gut and my brain are telling me otherwise. I’m going to stick to a 30 day reset with the AIP Protocol in an attempt to straighten things out, see how I feel, and then slowly introduce things back in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Go to the gym (more than once)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Biggest perk of being in NYC: there are two gyms on the same block that I live. No excuses. If I’m spending $20 a month on a gym membership, I need to spend 20 hours a month (at least) in there. My knees aren’t what they used to be, and having a job that has me stuck at a desk for eight hours isn’t exactly helping me maintain my current physical status.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Learn to play the guitar/tennis/rock climb/etc…&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I miss music. I miss being active. I used to be really good at both of those things, and it’s darn well time I brought them back into my life. Going to the gym is all well and good, but it should be for the goal of helping me get better at an activity I love, or don’t know that I love yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Get a tech job&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve dug my grave, now it’s time to lie in it. I quit my job, jumped off the deep end, and now it’s time to convince not only myself but others that I have skills that are useful and employable. I’m going to finish reading Eloquent Javascript, I’m going to stop having panic attacks at every Leet Code challenge, and I’m going to finally understand algorithms. Gonna do it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Stop spending hours on social media&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why do I do this? Why do I care? It’s like my brain doesn’t know what to do if it’s not constantly entertained. I’m going to get a bedside clock so that I’m not tempted to stay in bed and stare at my phone. I’m going to start being more aware of my knee jerk reaction to open those apps. I’m going to find something more useful with my time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are so many other things that I could list here, but I feel like this is a good start for the next few months, which is how I’m going to do this. A year is a very long time, and can seem daunting. A few months though, that’s not bad. I can reward myself after a few months, re-evaluate my goals, and start again. We’ll see how it goes!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 03 Jan 2016 07:09:09 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://linzjax.github.io/my-experiences/outreachy/2016/01/03/New-Years-Cliche.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://linzjax.github.io/my-experiences/outreachy/2016/01/03/New-Years-Cliche.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>my-experiences</category>
        
        <category>outreachy</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Research, Rethink, and Redesign</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“Avoid pixel-pushing at all costs – your job is to solve problems. View your work through that lens at all times. […] Accurately defining the problem goes a long way towards solving it.” - &lt;a href=&quot;http://somerandomdude.com/2012/01/10/transition-from-development-to-design/&quot;&gt;J.P. Onori&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;getting-started&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Getting started&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s week three of my internship with Cadasta, and I have been working on a complete redesign of the UI for &lt;a href=&quot;http://fieldpapers.org/&quot;&gt;Field Papers&lt;/a&gt;. Field Papers is an open source mapping tool that allows users to select areas on an atlas grid to be printed out, taken into the field, and then loaded back onto Field Papers. The concept of Field Papers is simple in theory, and it wasn’t until I started actually trying to improve it that I realized how complicated it was, but I’ll talk more about that in the next blog post (teasers!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;As I started digging into Field Papers there were a few &lt;em&gt;seemingly&lt;/em&gt; simple issues that stood out to me:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1) The map was way too small to actually be able to successfully navigate the atlas grid positioning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2) The atlas grid movement was completely disconnected from the map movement, which was confusing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3) The process was broken down into three separate steps, and could be consolidated into a single page site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4) Adding rows and columns was complicated by the fact that the buttons ran away from you as you clicked on them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the suggestion of my mentor Ian, I focused on three ways to solve most of these problems: &lt;strong&gt;“demodalisation”&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;“big map”&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;“better UI interaction model”&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Demodalization involves combining all three map composition steps onto a single page, and doing away with the “wizard” mode. Big map, rather unsurprisingly, consists of turning the current tiny map view port into a full screen map view. This will give the user much more flexibility and room to maneuver. Creating a better UI interaction model has turned out to be much more complicated and less straight forward than anticipated. But, again, I will discuss this in more detail in my next post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Addressing these issues needed to start with creating a full screen map display that could incorporate all possible map interactions onto a single page. Rather than jumping straight into building, I started with research, sketches and wireframes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;research&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Research&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first task was to see &lt;a href=&quot;http://linzjax.github.io/fieldpapers/notes-page/&quot;&gt;what other people were doing&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div width=&quot;100%&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gallery-box&quot;&gt;
		&lt;div class=&quot;gallery-images&quot;&gt;
			&lt;div class=&quot;image&quot;&gt;
				&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/FogukeV.png&quot; /&gt;
			&lt;/div&gt;
			&lt;div class=&quot;image&quot;&gt;
				&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/d4BSjNQ.png&quot; /&gt;
			&lt;/div&gt;
			&lt;div class=&quot;image&quot;&gt;
				&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/fIX7Fz3.png&quot; /&gt;
			&lt;/div&gt;
			&lt;div class=&quot;image&quot;&gt;
				&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/NIIn93o.png&quot; /&gt;
			&lt;/div&gt;
			&lt;div class=&quot;image&quot;&gt;
				&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/p3ICXGH.png&quot; /&gt;
			&lt;/div&gt;
			&lt;div class=&quot;image&quot;&gt;
				&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/aWzWT2l.png&quot; /&gt;
			&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gallery-lightbox hidden&quot;&gt;
	&lt;div class=&quot;gallery-lightbox-image&quot;&gt;
		&lt;img src=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;[&lt;em&gt;Examples of other websites with large scale maps. Most of them include a large side menu.&lt;/em&gt;]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Turns out that there’s not a whole lot of variation in the world of full screen maps. Unfortunately, there can’t be. If the goals is to allow the user to interact with the map, layouts and menus should be as unobtrusive as possible. There’s no need to be clever and cute. Just get out of the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;After examining what the current trends are, I came to a few conclusions:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only use lightbox menus for specific purposes. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	There were a few sites that used them for every action. It turned out to be distracting and frustrating. Not only were they in the way of the map view, they didn’t allow me to quickly flip back and forth between actions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Icons without explanation can be more confusing that they’re worth. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	I’ve run across this in a few apps, where in attempt to be as clean and streamlined as possible they turn all of their buttons into icons. This is all well and good, but only if it’s &lt;em&gt;extremely clear&lt;/em&gt; exactly what each icon represents. (I’m looking at you viscocam….)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Placement of menus should be simple and consistent. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	Having menus along all four walls of the browser window feels cluttered, and doesn’t allow your eyes to rest. Try to keep it limited to two walls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having the option to toggle whether or not the menu is visible is nice. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	However, and this goes along with the icon point, it should be clear how to trigger this interaction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Separate actions into different menus only if it makes sense. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	You want to make sure the separations make sense and are organized in a manner that’s not confusing to the user.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re ever uncertain, include a help section. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	If you think any of the interaction or icons might be confusing, include a help section. Heck, even if you don’t think it’s confusing, &lt;em&gt;include a help section&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;rethink&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rethink&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After my initial research and with these notes in mind, I settled down to do a quick 20 minute sketch session. The purpose of this exercise was to get as many ideas as I could in the allotted time, and to not stop until the timer was done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;instagram-media&quot; data-instgrm-captioned=&quot;&quot; data-instgrm-version=&quot;6&quot; style=&quot; background:#FFF; border:0; border-radius:3px; box-shadow:0 0 1px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.5),0 1px 10px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.15); margin: 1px; max-width:658px; padding:0; width:60%; width:-webkit-calc(60% - 2px); width:calc(60% - 2px);&quot;&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;padding:8px;&quot;&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; background:#F8F8F8; line-height:0; margin-top:40px; padding:47.4074074074% 0; text-align:center; width:100%;&quot;&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; background:url(data:image/png;base64,iVBORw0KGgoAAAANSUhEUgAAACwAAAAsCAMAAAApWqozAAAAGFBMVEUiIiI9PT0eHh4gIB4hIBkcHBwcHBwcHBydr+JQAAAACHRSTlMABA4YHyQsM5jtaMwAAADfSURBVDjL7ZVBEgMhCAQBAf//42xcNbpAqakcM0ftUmFAAIBE81IqBJdS3lS6zs3bIpB9WED3YYXFPmHRfT8sgyrCP1x8uEUxLMzNWElFOYCV6mHWWwMzdPEKHlhLw7NWJqkHc4uIZphavDzA2JPzUDsBZziNae2S6owH8xPmX8G7zzgKEOPUoYHvGz1TBCxMkd3kwNVbU0gKHkx+iZILf77IofhrY1nYFnB/lQPb79drWOyJVa/DAvg9B/rLB4cC+Nqgdz/TvBbBnr6GBReqn/nRmDgaQEej7WhonozjF+Y2I/fZou/qAAAAAElFTkSuQmCC); display:block; height:44px; margin:0 auto -44px; position:relative; top:-22px; width:44px;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt; &lt;p style=&quot; margin:8px 0 0 0; padding:0 4px;&quot;&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/p/_FByZCy9GR/&quot; style=&quot; color:#000; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; font-style:normal; font-weight:normal; line-height:17px; text-decoration:none; word-wrap:break-word;&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Sketchy sketch is sketchy. #outreachy #noideawhatimdoing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p style=&quot; color:#c9c8cd; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px; margin-bottom:0; margin-top:8px; overflow:hidden; padding:8px 0 7px; text-align:center; text-overflow:ellipsis; white-space:nowrap;&quot;&gt;A photo posted by Linz Jax (@linzjaxx) on &lt;time style=&quot; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px;&quot; datetime=&quot;2015-12-09T16:56:40+00:00&quot;&gt;Dec 9, 2015 at 8:56am PST&lt;/time&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; defer=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//platform.instagram.com/en_US/embeds.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This exercise prevented me from spending much time focusing on any one idea, which prevented me from becoming attached and letting that influence all of my subsequent decisions. It also prevented me from worrying about &lt;em&gt;completing&lt;/em&gt; each design idea. That way, when I started building wireframes I could choose the best options out of a pile of ideas and &lt;em&gt;then&lt;/em&gt; allow myself to finish them. A lot of the sketches ended up looking the same, but they still fed ideas once I actually started building out the models. There aren’t many options when it comes to being unobtrusive, and that’s ok.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During this process, I also brainstormed different ways each interaction could be designed. When does a dropdown vs. buttons make sense? Are there ways that tasks can be separated into different actions (map adjustment actions vs. saving and note-taking actions).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://rippedshakespear.mybalsamiq.com/projects/testing/zoom%20one.jpeg?version=3&amp;amp;etag=Z.sD2JZ1pxArJw4Q9iBMzMSqTlptAQHg&quot; alt=&quot;interactions&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;redesign&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Redesign&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once I was done with that I moved onto wireframes. I used &lt;a href=&quot;https://balsamiq.com/&quot;&gt;Balsamiq&lt;/a&gt; to build my &lt;a href=&quot;https://rippedshakespear.mybalsamiq.com/projects/testing/prototype/large%20left%20menue?key=a58b5f9011225b47db50f4fcf34c7cffdd2941cc&quot;&gt;wireframes&lt;/a&gt;, and oh my gosh it was magical. Incredibly easy to use, and little to no learning curve. Since this was the first time I had really worked with a wireframing tool, I started with the initially suggested design (with a few tweaks of my own). After that, I tried to implement as many different designs as I could, and ended up with about eight. I tried to make several that were very different, as well as a few I knew just straight up wouldn’t work. I wanted to build these anyway just to see &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; it wouldn’t work and what it was about these designs that made me uncomfortable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;These are a few examples of uncomfortable designs:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;gallery-box&quot;&gt;
	&lt;div class=&quot;gallery-images&quot;&gt;
		&lt;div class=&quot;image&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;https://rippedshakespear.mybalsamiq.com/projects/testing/round%20the%20outside%20menus.jpeg?version=2&amp;amp;etag=BeCO0B5dMODWGAMxwP9YXg_Gv5hIe5fm&amp;amp;key=a58b5f9011225b47db50f4fcf34c7cffdd2941cc&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;div class=&quot;image&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;https://rippedshakespear.mybalsamiq.com/projects/testing/weird%20top%20menu.jpeg?version=4&amp;amp;etag=qp3WHKbUxv50L.Fy1vIjOgxBAyOiW.CN&amp;amp;key=a58b5f9011225b47db50f4fcf34c7cffdd2941cc&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;div class=&quot;image&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;https://rippedshakespear.mybalsamiq.com/projects/testing/Top%20banner%20and%20%5Blightbox%5D.jpeg?version=8&amp;amp;etag=.cmR5zy86tMTcZVMEWUMU9hHFpLSE.tF&amp;amp;key=a58b5f9011225b47db50f4fcf34c7cffdd2941cc&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Image one&lt;/strong&gt;: You can’t see anything because the text lacks a background. Also, by placing the menu all the way around the edges your eyes are never given the chance to rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Image two&lt;/strong&gt;: The design just feels old, and while the positioning of the options are similar to the original Field Papers, it doesn’t feel like an improvement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Image three&lt;/strong&gt;: While initially I liked this design, it still presents the problem of tasks being separated a bit too harshly. It also doesn’t allow the user to write notes until they’re &lt;em&gt;done&lt;/em&gt; with the map, which is not ideal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After pushing myself to come up with as many ideas as possible, I was then able to narrow down my selection to three, and have a much better idea of &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; I preferred these designs over others. These were my final three:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This first one combines all of the task into one side menu. Everything is in one place, easily found, and always present. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img width=&quot;100%&quot; src=&quot;https://rippedshakespear.mybalsamiq.com/projects/testing/large%20left%20menue.jpeg?version=7&amp;amp;etag=NIJfjEYtJfOwh0jkwcmrRA_p04lKOc.A&amp;amp;key=a58b5f9011225b47db50f4fcf34c7cffdd2941cc&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This second one separates all of the actions into their own icon, allowing the user to think of them as different components to be tweaked on at a time. Stays as unobtrusive as possible.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img width=&quot;100%&quot; src=&quot;https://rippedshakespear.mybalsamiq.com/projects/testing/umap%20esqu%20%5Bpaper%5D.jpeg?version=3&amp;amp;etag=KSrrkEWdLWvb368g6.7NMTpzL7VUwKdn&amp;amp;key=a58b5f9011225b47db50f4fcf34c7cffdd2941cc&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This third one combines the first two ideas. It separates the actions into two categories, and provides a more solid menu to navigate. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img width=&quot;100%&quot; src=&quot;https://rippedshakespear.mybalsamiq.com/projects/testing/Left%20button%20right%20menu%20%5Bgrid%5D.jpeg?version=4&amp;amp;etag=hwonxcPIL_sIkJgerw8MkR3msBQ3iWrk&amp;amp;key=a58b5f9011225b47db50f4fcf34c7cffdd2941cc&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After talking it over with the Cadasta team, we ended up deciding on the first one. It ensures that all of the options are present, and completely removes the issue of modalization that was so problematic with the initial Field Papers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-thoughts&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Final thoughts&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was glad that I had the time to spend on going through this process. It allowed me to really think through all of the decisions I was making, rather than just running with whatever idea popped into my head first. Also, designing out in the open was valuable because it prevented me from developing this idea that these designs were &lt;em&gt;mine&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;precious&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;private&lt;/em&gt;. It allowed me to get comfortable with other people’s thoughts and opinions, and my designs only improved as a result.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So on to the next step! I am currently working on building a stand alone version of the tool to see how it actually behaves. Up next: The messy reality of UI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until next time,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cheers!&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 24 Dec 2015 08:33:09 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://linzjax.github.io/outreachy/2015/12/24/research-rethink-redesign.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://linzjax.github.io/outreachy/2015/12/24/research-rethink-redesign.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>outreachy</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Hello Outreachy</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;It’s been two months since I applied, one month since I found out I got accepted, and four days since the beginning of the Outreachy internship, and yet somehow, &lt;em&gt;somehow&lt;/em&gt; I’m still in denial about the fact that it’s actually happening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;But it is.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;How cool is that?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I’ve set aside my denial and decided to tell the world about my Outreachy journey. (Also, it’s a requirement of the internship, but I would have done it anyway. No really. Don’t look at me like that.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I was finishing up my batch at the Recurse Center, reality was starting to set in. If I really want to turn this hobby into a career, I have to start convincing other people (and myself) that I know what I’m doing. Outreachy seemed like a great place to start.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those that don’t know, &lt;a href=&quot;https://gnome.org/outreachy/&quot;&gt;Outreachy&lt;/a&gt; is a project that works to help underrepresented members of the tech community get involved in open source. You get to spend three months working with one of their partner companies on a project they’ve outlined. Open source has been an integral part of my journey to become a developer (see my &lt;a href=&quot;http://linzjax.github.io/my/experiences/2015/10/29/why-open-source-is-important-for-new-coders.html&quot;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt; for more open source banner waving), and I was excited by the opportunity to continue working within the community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So here I am, and I am so excited to be working with Cadasta! I’m thrilled to have the opportunity to combine design and development as I work with their team to rethink and redesign Field Papers’ UI. Over the next few weeks I’ll be blogging about my progress and musings along the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First installment: Research, rethink and redesign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until next time!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 10 Dec 2015 07:09:09 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://linzjax.github.io/outreachy/2015/12/10/hello-outreachy.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://linzjax.github.io/outreachy/2015/12/10/hello-outreachy.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>outreachy</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Reflections on Recurse Center</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;And just like that it was over. If you had told me a year ago that I would quit my job, move to New York and attend a completely self-directed three month “writers retreat” for programmers, I would have laughed nervously and not made eye contact. Yet here I am, makin’ eye contact like a pro. It’s been an unbelievable three months. I’ve made an amazing group of friends, and learned so much it makes my head hurt to think about it. I went into Recurse thinking GUI was a way to describe brownies and came out of it being able to comfortably construct full-stack applications like a boss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reflecting back on my experience, I realized that there were a lot of things I wish I had known, or maybe had a heads up for what to expect. So, for future Recursers: here are my thoughts. Hopefully they’ll help someone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. It’s ok to spend time just learning.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I got to Recurse I was asked over and over again “So what are you working on?”. It wasn’t until the second half of my batch that I realized this is Recurse equivalent of “how are you doing?”. It wasn’t meant to be intimidating. It wasn’t meant to suggest that I had to have a project idea right then and there. It was genuinely because people were interested. That being said, it was still horribly intimidating. I barely knew enough JavaScript to put together a tictactoe game. How was I going to come up with a full scale project?!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m going to tell you a little secret: what you’re working on doesn’t have to be a project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spent the first few weeks going through Node.js, Mongodb and Express tutorials, making sure that I really understood how they worked, and only then did I start working on projects. Recurse isn’t a startup factory, you don’t need to constantly be churning out some shiny new thing. It’s good to set goals, and it’s goood to have things you want to accomplish, but a good project could be going through all of Eloquent JavaScript.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, make sure you don’t spend the entire time with your nose tucked into a tutorial. Find someone else who wants to learn the same thing. Find someone who already knows about this stuff and ask them questions if you’re confused. There are people at Recurse. Use them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. Don’t be afraid to ask questions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I first got to Recurse, I was terrified of asking questions. Being rather new to programming, I assumed my questions were stupid, I was wasting people’s time, and they were silently wondering what the hell I was doing at Recurse if I didn’t already know these things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After finally getting up the courage to start asking, I was amazing at how excited people were to help. Recurse is filled with people that are interested in learning, and excited about others learning as well, and they want to help! Rather than banging my head against my keyboard hoping Google would come up with some magic tutorial, I could ask someone to explain, and then continue to explain if I didn’t get it the first time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, I’ve learned to love the phrase “I don’t know what that means”. You always learn something new, and if that person isn’t quite sure either, you get to learn together! It’s the best.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. Work with other people&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pairing with people is scary. The first time I did I found myself replaying it in my head going “Oh god was I annoying? Did I slow them down? Was this actually something they wanted to work on?”. What I can tell you now is not to worry about it. Talk about what you’re interested in working on ahead of time and make sure that you both have the same goals. If you want to dive deep and really understand things, and they just want to finish the project, you’re not going to have a great time pairing. If you didn’t enjoy pairing with someone, don’t worry about it. If they don’t ask you to pair again, don’t worry about it. It’s all a learning experience, and there are no wrong decisions, except the decision not to work with anyone while you’re there. Mostly because you need to know how. If you want to program as a career, you need to know how to pair, and Recurse is a safe place to practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. Shits and giggles programming is just the best&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were several times that I was working on a “real” project, hating my life, and finally ditching it to build something fun and stupid. These fun and stupid projects ended up being some of my favorite. It’s okay to have fun. It’s okay to build something useless just because you feel like it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5. Learn to walk away&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re staring angrily at your computer screen, slamming your keys desperately trying to fix a bug that you know would be easily fixed if you could just figure out what the stupid thing is doing wrong. Walk. Away. Get up from your seat, pace the room, grab a cup of tea, ask people if they’re interested in a coffee run, anything. Just walk away. Your brain has this amazing ability to figure things out, but only if you give it a chance to recuperate. You’ll be amazed what comes to you after you’ve walked away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;6. Talk to people!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m the worst at networking. I think it’s silly and I find small talk painful at best. However, for the first few weeks of Recurse I made it a point to talk to as many different people as possible. It was scary, but everyone was incredibly open, and I learned a lot about my fellow Recursers. One of things that makes Recurse unique is that everyone is “the new person”, so they’re all looking for someone to talk to. It’s like a beautiful hand crafted artisanal friend group made specifically for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you feel like you haven’t really made connections with anyone immediately, give it time. Some of my best friends from Recurse I didn’t talk to until the second half.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;7. Do things that scare the hell out of you.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of the following points lead into this: Practice being brave.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recurse is one of the most supporting, loving, non-judgmental environments I’ve ever been in. No one’s doing a “thing”. No one’s looking at you funny. Everyone’s going to be excited when you join in and try new things. Before Recurse I had never sung a song at karaoke by myself. Ever. Not once. But the first karaoke night I decided I was going to do it because everyone else was having fun and no one cared that we weren’t going to be auditioning for American Idol any time soon, and everyone cheered so loud after every song that you felt like you were the biggest rock star in the world. My voice cracked, I was scared out of my mind, but I survived. Not only did I survive, I got thoroughly addicted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While this point acts as a plug for karaoke night (please keep this tradition going!), it’s mostly to highlight the importance of doing the things that scare you. Avoiding things because “you’re not good at them” is silly. It’s a fixed mindset that’s going to keep you from rocking out like Christina Aguilera wishes she could. Be brave! Do things!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recurse is amazing. You’re amazing. You’d make a great pair. If you’re thinking about going, you totally should. If you’re still unsure, or have more questions, please don’t hesitate to ask me anything. I have so much advice and many stories to share. My next blog will be on the scary bits of Recurse (don’t worry, they’re not that scary). Until then,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cheers!&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 11 Nov 2015 13:30:09 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://linzjax.github.io/my/experiences/outreachy/2015/11/11/reflections-on-recurse-center.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://linzjax.github.io/my/experiences/outreachy/2015/11/11/reflections-on-recurse-center.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>My</category>
        
        <category>experiences</category>
        
        <category>outreachy</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
